<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sanjeev Kumar</title>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com</link>
    <description>The Social Coder</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2009 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
    <generator>The mighty Wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>A walk in Brussels</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-11-25-Brussels-Belgium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2009 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-11-25-Brussels-Belgium/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Arun and Anagha, our family friends, visited us in Brussels and we decided to do a little site seeing while they were around. Brussels has grown from a 10th-century fortress town to a sizeable city. It has a lot of popular places that a lot of tourists come to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started our site seeing from the famous Atomium which is in Hayzel and is not very from where we live in Brussels. Rajni cooked some Parathas and snacks to carry along for site seeing. Later that day we went to see this place called Grand Place which is at walking distance from our place. It was a day well spent with family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some pics from the tour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span2&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-PJUjJY7H-5Q/UR--ouCHg5I/AAAAAAAAZYY/6RmJksypA7Q/w352-h264-p-o/P1040813.JPG&quot; &gt;&lt;/span2&gt;
&lt;span2&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-doW0wcSR15c/UR-_CgQ51OI/AAAAAAAAZZQ/4QNtJtl-ays/w345-h259-p-o/P1030536.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;/span2&gt;
&lt;span2&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-_7_x0VNACsI/UR--4ZuJ2LI/AAAAAAAAZY4/eX_c7crLv7c/w359-h269-p-o/P1040558.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;/span2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Day trip to the largest city of Netherlands - Amsterdam</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-01-01-Amsterdam-Netherlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-01-01-Amsterdam-Netherlands/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The city of glamour, weed and fun, Amsterdam, was the last site that was on our agenda. Unlike Arun&amp;#39;s basic nature, he was very accommodating :-) and agreed to almost all our plans and gave up giving anymore advices for site seeing. We all surrendered to Rajni&amp;#39;s agenda of feeding grains to pigeons on dam square and get some snaps clicked on the giant &amp;quot; I AMSTERDAM&amp;quot; structure, followed by a tour of famous red light district of Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending sometime at Dam Square we moved towards the Bloeman market which is known for wide variety of flowers and souvenirs items. We bought some small wooden shoes, small windmill replicas and famous cheese of Holland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that we started asking people about the &amp;quot;I AMSTERDAM&amp;quot; structure. Nobody seemed to knew about any such thing in Amsterdam. Eventually we got some hint about it that it was near &amp;quot;Rijks&amp;quot; museum. On the way to the Rijks museum we passed through the famous Vondel Park and clicked some snaps there. It was freezing cold in the park as it was open from all sides. We were surprised to see some people jogging there in shots and plane track suits. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After asking a few more people we finally made it to the museum and the &amp;quot;I AMSTERDAM&amp;quot; place. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We clicked some snaps there and after Rajni was satisfied, we moved ahead to see the red light area of Amsterdam. It started raining on the way and we were carrying only one umbrella which was obviously not enough to accommodate all of us.  We were also very hungry so decided to get into some restaurant for some snacks and stay there until it stops raining.
It was all non-vegetarian restaurant, so Anagha did not have anything accept for few biscuits with Mayonnaise. She is too sweet to complain about anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually we all reached the place that we all wanted to see and that was Red Light district. We didn&amp;#39;t need to ask anyone about this place as it was all too obvious as soon as we reached there. Thankfully, Ranit was sleeping in his pram so I was spared from answering all those questions that he would have asked. We spend some half an hour in those streets and then started back for Amsterdam railway station from where we had to catch our train for Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the most fun filling and full filling trip that we have had in Europe and we highly appreciate Arun and Anagha for being the perfect host. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward for some more site seeing tours of Nederlands during tulip season. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A day trip to Aquatopia at Antwerp, Brussels</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-11-30-Aquatopia-Aquarium/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-11-30-Aquatopia-Aquarium/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aquatopia is a popular educational attraction in central Antwerp, Belgium. It features a set of aquariums, along with recreations of other marine habitats, including swamps, rain forests, river deltas, and coral reefs. Aquatopia also includes a number of special exhibits covering sharks, nautilus, and mysteries of the deep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went to see Aquatopia with Arun and Anagha who were visting us from Netherlands. It was a nice trip and Ranit was so excited after seeing so many fishes and other sea animals. Shark show was amazing and after that show Ranit kept asking that if shark can eat dad if he jumps into that water. Ranit also managed to get a Dolphin puzzle as a gift from Arun and that kept Ranit busy for quite a few days. While I am writing this Ranit is busy assembling the same Dolphin puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domtoren Utrecht, Netherlands</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-12-30-Domtoren-Utrecht/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2009 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-12-30-Domtoren-Utrecht/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We were waiting for this long weekend from quite some time and finally it came with a bang. It was quite an event full weekend and will stay in our memories for a long long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trip started with a little trouble as we boarded the wrong train from Brussels.  The tickets that we had were for a normal train but we boarded the super fast (Thalys) train instead. Luckily the train manager was kind enough to let us go without charging us anything for boarding that train. He could have charged us around 50 Euros for this but he didn&amp;#39;t want to spoil our Christmas and allowed us to continue our journey. I love Christmas, god exists :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it was a thalys train it hardly took us any time to reach Rotterdam and eventually to our final destination Utrecht where Arun was already waiting for us with his Italian umbrella as it was raining. It was around 11 AM of the Christmas day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the delicious lunch prepared by Anagha (Spicy Dum Aalu) we went out to see the tallest church Dom &amp;quot;Domtoren&amp;quot; in  Netherlands. It was hardly a few yards from Arun&amp;#39;s house. It was very windy and slippery outside the church but we still managed to click some snaps for our album. Thanks to Rajni&amp;#39;s Swiss umbrella. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we saw the church Arun suggested to walk around the city a bit and showed us a few interesting places in Utrecht. On the way he told about how Greg and he used to roam around till 4 Am in that area after they were refused entry in the pubs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arun also told about why Nederland people are best water management experts in the word and how it is still rising to prosperity in spite of having a lot of area under the sea levels. In the back of my mind I started thinking about our Indian states like Orisa and Bihar where every year we suffer huge losses of lives and property due to floods. Why can&amp;#39;t we learn and implement the solutions that have been implemented successfully in Netherlands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranit was also having a wonderful time on the streets.  Just then it started drizzling and we decided to move back to Arun&amp;#39;s luxurious :-)  apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arun had already planned for a daaru party on Christmas and he had to do certain arrangements for that. Ranit wanted to see his favorite movie &amp;quot;Hanuman Returns&amp;quot; for the thousandth time so we all joined him for that on you tube. Actually, I also like that movie and can watch it again and again. 
Overall it was an excellent start and we all were  very happy and excited and were looking forward for the next event which was &amp;quot;The daaru party&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The windmills of Kinderdijk, Netherlands</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-12-31-Kinderdijk-Netherlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2009 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2009-12-31-Kinderdijk-Netherlands/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had heard a lot about Netherlands wind mills that were built more than two centuries ago and are still into existence.For many centuries these windmills played an important role in the drainage &amp;amp; subsequent reclamation of the lands in NL. These windmills were already on our agenda for this weekend. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arun checked the bus and train route and selected the best way to reach Kiderdijk. Bus was a little more convenient than train as it was the direct route. So we left for the bus stop from where we were to board the bus  number 90 for Kinderdijk. I remember the bus number because it saved us some 40 € for the travel. For some reasons, that day it was free travel on that route so we didn&amp;#39;t have to pay anything for our trip to Kinderdijk. Arun was excited and could hardly control his happiness when the driver told him that it was a free day. I also had a similar or may be even more intense reaction when Arun told me about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an hour and twenty minutes journey we reached Kinderdijk. From the bus stop itself we could see some windmills. The weather was very pleasant that day and it added to our pleasure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we all used the toilet (using a single 50 cent coin) we were all set to explore and appreciate the beauty of the 19 windmills that were there. It was very scenic and calm place and spent some some quality time there and clicked some nice snaps for my photo album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending about couple of hours and after clicking photographs around the windmills in all possible posses like all Indians do, we wrapped up and decided to go to Rotterdam to see some more sites. Of-course we boarded the same bus route number 90. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arun suggested a few more sites that we could have visited on the same day but I didn&amp;#39;t feel like going anywhere as Ranit had already slept in his pram and it would have been a bit of inconvenience for him. Besides I was still awestruck after seeing the beautiful and natural windmills of Kinderdijk and didn&amp;#39;t want to let thyis feeling go for some more time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We realized that we had not eaten anything after the breakfast and decided to get some chicken kebabs and french fries. After spoiling the floor of kebab shop with the chicken and bread from our kebabs we decided to call it a day and started our journey for Arun&amp;#39;s apartment. We also had to pack our bags for next day as we had planned to see Amsterdam city and board the train for Brussels directly from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall it was another wonderful day!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>London, England</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-05-20-London-England/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-05-20-London-England/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been more than a month since our London trip ended but the memories of the trip are still so fresh as if it was Yesterday. So before my recollections of the trip fade away, I am putting it down in my travelog. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the trip started with a very positive news from London about Simi &amp;amp; Rohit (My sis-in-law) getting blessed with a baby boy. I was excited to join them in London during these happy moments. Rajni and Ranit were already in London from past one month so seeing them after so long was itself a great feeling that I was looking forward to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we didn&amp;#39;t have a very well planned agenda for our 7 days of London sight seeing trips, as I was relying completely on Rohit for that. Thanks to Rohit for planning all our trips perfectly so that we can see as much of London as possible without exerting ourselves to death :-). It worked out very well for us and we will cherish the memories from that trip forever.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on our first day we went to see the Kingston Riverside where we spent most of our time hanging out along the river side on that sunny day. While I was enjoying my beer, Rajni ensured that kids don&amp;#39;t jump into the river while feeding ducks :-). Afterall they are Indian kids so anything is possible. Specially Ranit is quite capable of doing such stuff. It was overall a relaxed day where we warmed up ourselves for the rest of our trip.  One thing that I remember from this day was these two old women, probably in their late 80&amp;#39;s, sitting on a bench under the most beautiful tree on the riverside. That was the perfect place to click some snaps, so we decided to wait for sometime for these ladies to move. We waited for some 4 hrs and eventually gave up the hope to get a snap in that area. These women were like glued together with the bench and sat there throughout the day. For my satisfaction I went a little closer and was relieved to see that both were alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our second day we saw a lot many popular places of London like O2 Arena, Greenwich Observatory, CuttySark and Canary Wharf. Rajni liked the skyscrapers rising from the Thames river in Canary Wharf and Ranit and I liked Greenwich Observatory for its greenery and huge parks and play areas for kids. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third day was Rajni&amp;#39;s birthday and was reserved for the best sites of London. That day we visited London Bridge, Big Ben, London Eye, Footbridge on Thames and the famous Tate Art Gallery. London looked very beautiful and tiny from within the LondonEye capsule.  We unanimously agree for London Eye to be our favorite from this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were a little tired so decided to rest on the forth day. We also visited Usha Didi&amp;#39;s house on that day where Ranit got a foot scooter as a gift. He was so exited and possessive about it that he refused to open it fearing that Gungun (Simi&amp;#39;s daughter) will take it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifth day we saw Buckingham Palace, Hyde Park, Saint James Park, Madam Tussuad, Trafalgar square and Oxford street. In Madam Tussuad I got the opportunity to pose with, hold and kiss the likes of Julia Roberts and Angelina Joli while Rajni was hanging out with Johnny Depp &amp;amp; Brad pit. Ranit found a hiding place near the legs of Marilyn Monroe. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sixth day was the most special one when Rohit drove us to Brighton beach which was some 60 miles from their house. Gungun was also with us on this trip. It was a nice sunny day again like on all other days during our trip. This was kind-of rare during that part of the year. We spent full day on this pebbled beach and it was so much fun. We spent some time playing some games in this casino-for-kids kind of thing. Gungun managed to win a few gifts from the games which were later distributed between Gungun and Ranit. Rohit also demonstrated his skills by winning us couple of toy dolphins by beating all his competitors in the fish race. He did that not once but twice and second time I was also competing with him. He won by a second or two. I was at second position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seventh day we spent at home. Usha Didi and Jija ji also joined us at Rohit&amp;#39;s house and in the evening Rohit stuffed us with a lot of chilled beer and delicious pork which he cooked himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gungun, Simi and Rohit were awesome hosts throughout our stay in London and we thoroughly enjoyed each and every minute that we spent there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A day trip to Dinant, belgium</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-06-07-Dinant-Belgium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-06-07-Dinant-Belgium/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week finally we got the opportunity to visit Dinant, which is a small town known for its natural beauty and some terrible historic events that happened there during late 1800s. Another relatively lesser know fact about this place is that Adolphe Sax, inventor of the saxophone was also born and brought up in the vicinity of Citadel fort, which is a prominent  tourist attraction in this region of Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a day trip. We left Brussels at around 10 AM and reached Dinant within an hour. Weather was very nice and sunny on that day. We started our tour by clicking some snaps of Citadel fort which was just about 400 meters from the station. Then we took a cable car tide to the top of the fort and spent a few hours there on the hill. Ranit had some great time on the swings in the play area for kids while we enjoyed the guided tour of the citadel fort. After getting down from Citadel we went to see the house of Adolphe Sax which still displays some of the original Saxophones that he made. We felt privileged for having got an opportunity to get some snaps clicked with the statue of Adolphe Sax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought some beers and snacks from a grocery store and then spent some time on the river side while enjoying the Beer and Sandwiches that Rajni had prepared and brought from home. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was overall a relaxed tour where we didn&amp;#39;t sweat ourselves too much and enjoyed it on a slow pace without having to run from one site to the other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few other scenic places, châteaus and a small beautiful village in that area, that we have saved for our next trip :-).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>History, heritage and beauty of Italy</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-07-07-Rome-Florence-Venice-Italy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-07-07-Rome-Florence-Venice-Italy/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long wait for summers and good holiday deals, we finalized our itinerary during last week of May. The trip was planned from 19th June till 26th June. This time we chose to stay at camping sites at the out skirts of Rome city centre and now I can say that it was a good decision as the camping was fun and we always had something to do after returning from our day trips from Rome and other places. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found Rome very close and comparable to our India, particularly Delhi, in a number of ways. The weather, the people, their hospitality, familiar and pleasant smell of the soil after it rained, helping and fun loving nature of people, houses with roof top television antennas and scooters everywhere were some of the few similarities that we observed. We explored the rich history of Rome for three days followed by an afternoon at Ostia Antica beach. The weather was at our side most of the times except for the first day when it rained throughout the day and last day when we nearly fainted due the hot sunny day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colosseum was the best place to see in Rome closely followed by Vatican City, Trevi fountain, Spanish steps and a few piazzas (Rectangular open areas in the city usually surrounded by restaurants and shops. Nice places to hang out with friends and observe city culture).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we went to Florence and just after checking in our hotel we went to see the leaning tower of Pisa. It was worth the visit and the white marble used in its construction reminded me of the Taj Mahal. We returned to Florence in the evening and kept roaming around in the city till late night while Ranit was having a nap in his Pram. It was fun. Florence has some very huge and beautiful old churches that we kept looking at in awe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Final place on our trip was Venice and we had spared around 3 days for this place. I am not exaggerating when I say that Venice was the most beautiful place that I have seen till now. Rajni seconds this feeling. We spent a lot of time on the boats. We also saw the making of Murano glass on Murano island and Rajni even bought a jewellery set as a souvenir from Murano. We walked through the streets deep inside the Venice city and thoroughly enjoyed our time there. Ice lollies proved a lot effective in beating the heat on venice during those sunny days. There is so much about the city to talk and write about; Some other time perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overridable methods need special care</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-08-29-Overiride-Carefully/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-08-29-Overiride-Carefully/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Allowing a method to be overridden should always be done intentionally, not by accident&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any method which is not private, static, or final can be overridden. Over-ridable methods, and any methods which call them, represent unusual places in your code, to which special attention must be paid. This is because sub-classing violates encapsulation, in the sense that it is possible for a subclass to break its superclass&amp;#39;s contract. If you do not intend a method to be overridden, then you should declare it as private, static, or final.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you do override a method, you should use the @Override annotation. This allows the compiler to verify that the method is indeed a valid override of an existing method. For example, your implementations of toString, equals, and hashCode should always use @Override in the method header. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A trip to the city of fashion, Paris</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-05-30-Paris-France/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-05-30-Paris-France/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally its a weekend and we have no plans except for going to the fancy dress show in Ranit&amp;#39;s school. So I have some time to pen down some moments from our Paris trip that we did earlier this month. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a lot of expectations from our trip when we left for Paris from Brussels. It was the city that I had thought about visiting at least once in this life while I was in junior school and when I first saw that movie &amp;quot;An evening in Paris&amp;quot; starring Shammi Kapoor. Of-course I am lying. But yes it was indeed a place where I wanted to be at least once and after our 5 days stay in Paris Trust me it is worth visiting at least once in your life. So if you happen to be in Europe for sometime for work or anything like that, DON&amp;#39;T MISS IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had got a good deal for staying in Paris for 4 nights. It was actually not in Paris but about 20 km out of it. However, the city is so well connected that you hardly realize it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We reached Paris on 13th May at around 12:30 PM. From there we directly went to our hotel, checked in and then left for a quick city tour. That  day we managed to see Defense Arc, Champs-Elysees, Arc De Triomphe and Concord. It was getting slightly darker and we were planning to call it a day. Just then we got our first glimpse of Eiffel Tower and we were fresh and energetic again and decided to see Eiffel from close before leaving for our hotel. In about 20 minutes and after changing couple of Metros we were there, right next to the Eiffel tower. It was stunningly beautiful. It was glowing in golden color with some white and purple lights twinkling all over it. We kept clicking photographs till both pairs of our batteries were dead. We had no option but to call it a day and leave for the hotel and because Ranit was also with us and it was already around 12 midnight it was a good decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next day we spent at Disneyland, where Ranit was having all the fun and we were enjoying the excitement and spark in his eyes that he was having while waiting for his turn on the rides. Another good day gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third day we was a few more beautiful places  like Montmatre, NotreDam, Bercy park and the wooden walking bridge over the Siene river of Paris. Also we couldn&amp;#39;t have enough of Eiffel tower on our first day in Paris, so decided to go there again and this time we spent some 2 hrs or more in the queue to get a ride to the top of Eiffel. Once  we were on the second floor of Eiffel and looked at the Paris city from there, we realized that it was worth the wait in the queue. We could not go to the top floor as that was closed for some maintenance :( probably for next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the forth day we admired the history and art crafted on the walls (&amp;amp; Roofs)of Chateau De Versailles. Later we spent a lot of time in the beautiful gardens around the palace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we were at our last day in Paris but the good news was that we had the full day in hand as our bus was leaving from Paris at 6 in the evening. On this day we visited Chateau De Vincennes followed by the Parc Floral de Paris. It is relatively lesser known park but we enjoyed the most here. It was very beautiful and has some nice scenic spots to click some decent snaps.   If you are with kids they will love it. We also saw St. Marten canal and Paris De Nord on this day before heading towards our bus. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just before we were to board our bus for Brussels and when I was feeling happy about being able to accomplish our trip within our allocated budget, Rajni started bargaining for a Perfume form Paris. Eventually we overshot our allocated budget by some 100 € :-(.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: I would like to thank this little french guy who helped us in reaching Champs-Elysees after we boarded the wrong bus and realized it half an hour later. It was difficult for him to make us understand(French Only Guy) the route so he came out of his way to make sure that we reach our destination safely . I learnt that language, nationality and color of skin is not a barrier if you are committed to help others, anywhere in this world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prefer composition over inheritance</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-08-09-Composition-Inheritance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-08-09-Composition-Inheritance/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trust me on this one, I have learnt it the hard way. To start with lets start with the understanding of the terms composition and inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Composition&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functionality of an object is made up of an aggregate of different classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In practice, this means holding a pointer to another class to which work is deferred&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaboration is implemented simply by forwarding all calls to an object field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has no dependence on implementation details of the object field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is more flexible, since it is defined dynamically at run-time, not statically at compile-time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inheritance&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functionality of an object is made up of it&amp;#39;s own functionality plus functionality from its parent classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sub-classing or inheritance has the following issues :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It violates encapsulation, since the implementations of the superclass and subclass become tightly coupled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new methods added to the superclass can break the subclass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;superclass and subclass need to evolve in parallel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;designing a class so that it may be safely extended takes extra work - extending a class not explicitly designed for such use is risky&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;different packages are often under the control of different programmers - extending a class in a different package is risky&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common exception is the template method design pattern. There, the safest style is to make all items in the abstract base class final, except for the single abstract method which needs to be implemented by the subclass.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use final liberally. Please do.</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-09-19-Use-Final-Liberally/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-09-19-Use-Final-Liberally/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Use the final keyword liberally to communicate your intent. The final keyword has more than one meaning :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a final class cannot be extended&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a final method cannot be overridden&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;final fields, parameters, and local variables cannot change their value once set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last case, &amp;quot;value&amp;quot; for primitives is understood in the usual sense, while &amp;quot;value&amp;quot; for objects means the object&amp;#39;s identity, not its state. Once the identity of a final object reference is set, it can still change its state, but not its identity. Declaring primitive fields as final automatically ensures thread-safety for that field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some habitually declare parameters as final, since this almost always is the desired behaviour. Others find this verbose, and of little real benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistently using final with local variables (when appropriate) can be useful as well. It brings attention to the non-final local variables, which usually have more logic associated with them (for example, result variables, accumulators, loop variables). Many find this verbose. A reasonable approach is to use final for local variables only if there is at least one non-final local variable in the method ; this serves to quickly distinguish the non-final local variables from the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using final :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clearly communicates your intent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allows the compiler and virtual machine to perform minor optimizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clearly flags items which are simpler in behavior - final says,  &amp;quot;If you are looking for complexity, you won&amp;#39;t find it here.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beware of floating point numbers</title>
      <link>http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-10-20-Beware-Of-Floating-Points/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2010 15:00:00 +0550</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.sanjeevonline.com/articles/2010-10-20-Beware-Of-Floating-Points/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outside of a scientific or engineering context, the use of float and double (and the corresponding wrapper classes Float and Double ) should likely be avoided. The fundamental problem is that rounding errors will always occur when using these data types - they are unavoidable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a typical business application, using float and double to represent money values is dangerous, because of these rounding issues. Instead, BigDecimal should usually be used to represent money. It is also a common practice to have utility classes like &amp;quot;MonetaryAmount.java&amp;quot; that are wrappers over &amp;quot;BigDecimal&amp;quot; class of the JDK and that provides helper methods and functionality as needed by the business application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an IBM article on this topic :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&amp;quot;...binary floating-point arithmetic should not be used for financial, commercial, and user-centric applications or web services because the decimal data used in these applications cannot be represented exactly using binary floating-point.&amp;quot;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an article by Brian Goetz :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&amp;quot;...it is a bad idea to use floating point to try to represent exact quantities like monetary amounts. Using floating point for dollars-and-cents calculations is a recipe for disaster. Floating point numbers are best reserved for values such as measurements, whose values are fundamentally inexact to begin with.&amp;quot; 
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>